Guide to the Park West Camera Club Records 1946-2017 PR 368
New-York Historical Society
Park West Camera Club records
1946-2017
New-York Historical Society
Park West Camera Club (New York, N.Y.)
PR 368
11.3 Linear feet in 3 document boxes, one flat box, and 11 flat files.
The Park West Camera Club records include newsletters (primarily 1984-2014), meeting minutes (primarily 1947-1959 and some from the late 1970s and early 1980s), and original member photography, among other documents. The club was founded in 1937 as an educational offering of the New York City YMCA's 63rd Street branch, and the organization continues, though now independent of the YMCA. Original photographs in the collection range from the 1940s into the early 2000s.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes newsletters and administrative records of the Park West Camera Club (PWCC), and examples of the photographs taken by its members. The records are not complete, but do hold substantial runs of important documents. The newsletters date primarily from 1984 to 2014. Minutes of meetings are primarily from 1947-1959, with some from the late 1970s and early 1980s. Some of the club's group activities are documented, most notably its 2015 exhibition Through Our Eyes and the 2017 exhibition celebrating PWCC's 80th anniversary. Original photographic prints by members comprise a significant part of the collection. These photographs range in date from the 1940s to the early 2000s.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in four series:
Series I. Newsletters (1984-2014)
Series II. Administrative Files (1946-1959, 1978-2017)
Series III. Club Activities and Exhibitions (1947-2017)
Series IV. Photography by Members (1940s-2000s)
Biographical / Historical
The Park West Camera Club was founded in 1937. Originally called the Hypo Hounds, the club began as an educational offering of the 63rd Street branch of the YMCA in New York City. The group changed its name to Park West Camera Club in 1952. It remained affiliated with the YMCA for several decades, until the 1990s or early 2000s. At the YMCA the group had a basement meeting space with equipment for developing photographs. This space was also used to house the organization's records and select member photography. In the 1990s, the basement space flooded, destroying many records and photographs, and damaging others. The incident spurred the creation of an Archives Committee led by Myrna Harrison-Changar, which eventually drew on the salvaged material to mount the exhibition Eight Decades of Photography in 2017 in celebration of PWCC's 80th anniversary. The exhibition was held at the Soho Gallery in Tribeca, where PWCC had taken up residence after it spun off from its YMCA affiliation. As of 2018, PWCC still meets weekly at the Gallery.
(The above note was based on information from the collection and from PWCC's website.)
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Park West Camera Club, 2018.
Clubs -- New York (State) -- New York.; Photographers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Photographs.; Park West Camera Club (New York, N.Y.) -- Archives
- Series I. Newsletters, 1984-2014; .5 Linear feet in one box
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains newsletters and documents that were sent out with newsletters from 1984-2014. These years seem to be complete, although there may be a few issues unaccounted for. Some newsletters from before 1984 and after 2014 can be found in Series II (Administrative Files).
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Newsletters (8 folders), 1984-2014 (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
- Series II. Administrative Files, 1946-1959, 1978-2017; .71 Linear feet in two boxes
  This series contains five sets of records maintained at various times over the course of PWCC's history. The first is a run of minutes of PWCC meetings, dating from 1946-1959. The second set includes the contents of binders maintained by the club's History Committee for years 1978-79 and 1979-80; these includes minutes, newsletters, member lists, competition results, and other documents for those years (see the more detailed content list at the folder level below). The third set includes minutes and newsletters from 1983-85, likely maintained by the Recording Secretary. The fourth set includes financial records (revenue, expenses) for 1978-88. The final set includes documents primarily from 2016-17 and relate to the activities of the Archive Committee then in place.
  As can be seen from the above description, there are substantial gaps in coverage. There are no minutes or other administrative records for 1960-77 and from after 1985. The few newsletters in this series add some earlier years to those found in Series I (1984 and later), but there remain gaps.
  This series is arranged by the sets of administrative records in the collection, which advance in rough chronological order, with sizable gaps in coverage.
  - Minutes, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1978-1979 Records, from Binder (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 15-19)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    This binder was a gift from Paul Perkus.
    Folders hold content taken from a 3-ring binder maintained by the club's historian for 1978-79, Dan Arthur: newsletters, meeting minutes, administrative correspondence, lists of general members, committees and committee members, event attendance counts, and slide and print competition grades.
  - 1979-1980 Records, from Binder (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 20-24)
    Folders hold content taken from a 3-ring binder, likely maintained by the chairperson of the History Committee for that year, Dan Arthur: membership and committee lists, newsletters, constitution (as adopted 1975 and amended through 1979), by-laws, meeting minutes, correspondence (including room reconstruction negotiations with the YMCA in connection with the Y's intent to have the PWCC share space with ceramics activities), YMCA photo competition & social activities (with a Christmas themed poem incorporating the names of all dues-paying members), member exhibitions (including a checklist of objects exhibited by PWCC members at the United Nations by invitation of the UN Staff Recreation Council), darkroom administration, score sheets for the black and white and color slides competitions, attendance records, and publicity flier.
  - 1983-1985 Records, from Binder (2 folders), 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    Folders hold content from binder likely maintained by Recording Secretary Lee Backer: newsletters, by-laws (as adopted 1980), and meeting minutes.
  - Finances, 1978-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Finances, 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Archive Committee Binder (2 folders), 2014-2017 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    Folders hold content from a binder likely maintained by club archivist Myrna Changar: program and checklist/pricelist for PWCC member exhibition "A Sense of Wonder" at the Ryan/Chelsea-Clinton Community Health Center (2016); print-out lists from database of photographer works in PWCC archives (2016-17); Soho Photo Gallery floor plan and a few related documents in connection with planning for the 80th anniversary show (2016); Archive Committee newsletters; record of donation to PWCC archives of Myron Brenton materials (2017); agendas, correspondence, minutes, and other documents of the Archive Committee (2016-17); constitution (revised as of 2012); and other documents.
- Series III. Club Activities and Exhibitions, 1947-2017; 1.84 Linear feet in two boxes plus flat files
  This series contains photographs, articles, and documents that showcase club activities and member achievements. The club activities range from photography excursions, club meetings and social outings, photography competitions, and PWCC exhibitions. Select member achievements are highlighted in newspaper articles, which are in very fragile condition. Some names found within the photo credits are confirmed members, while others are unconfirmed. There is also a folder on Otto Litzel, an honored club member, which also includes some background on the PWCC records. Significant exhibitions represented in this series are the Through Our Eyes exhibition of 2015 and the 2017 PWCC 80th anniversary show Eight Decades of Photography.
  The series is arranged by subject matter.
  - PWCC Photo Album Vol. III, 1984 June-November 5 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Contains snapshots from club outings, meetings, and events. Album titled Vol. III, which is the only volume from this set in N-YHS's possession.
  - Otto Litzel - Dinner, Speeches, Research, circa 2012 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Select Member Achievements, PWCC Press, 1947-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Primarily holds original clippings either related to PWCC or that include photographs credited to PWCC members. Some of these materials were reproduced for PWCC's historical exhibition "Through Our Eyes," which are found in the following folders. Other than clippings, original documents include a Metropolitan Camera Club Council member directory (1976), a YMCA/PWCC publicity flyer (1960s?), and a copy of the YMCA's newsletter "West Side" for April 17, 1947, which carries a photograph by a PWCC (then Hypo Hounds) member and a mention of the club and darkroom.
  - "Salon Exhibitors of the Park West C.C.", 1952-1957 (Folder FF-9)
    7 original oversize sheets listing exhibitors from PWCC during 1952-57, with columns for name of the photographer/"maker", name of salon, title of print or slide exhibited, and any award received. Otto Litzel appears perhaps most frequently.
  - "Through Our Eyes." Introductory Boards, 2015 (Folder FF-10)
    3 pasted-up boards with documents from the exhibition, including title, introduction, certificate reproductions, and prints of digital scans of "The Daydreamers" (1936) and "Field Trip" (1950s?).
  - "Through Our Eyes." Reproductions of Clippings & Documents from the 1940s-1990s (6 folders), 2015 (Box 2, Folder 8-13)
  - "Through Our Eyes." Photograph Prints (folder 1 of 2), 2015 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    7 black and white digital reproductions of gelatin silver prints, roughly 8 x 11 inches. M.D. Arnold "Little Girl with a Bonnet" (undated) (2 prints); Wally Arrington "Little Brother" (1968); Dan Arthur "Lady with a Necklace" (undated); Ann Jackson "New York Summer" (undated); Ray Long "Central Park Skyline" (1947); and Dan MacLaughlin "Sunnyside Yards" (1964).
  - "Through Our Eyes." Photograph Prints (folder 2 of 2), 2015 (Folder FF-10)
    6 black and white digital reproductions of gelatin silver prints, roughly 16 x 11 inches. M.D. Arnold "Little Girl with a Bonnet" (undated) (2 prints); Wally Arrington "Little Brother" (1968); Ann Jackson "New York Summer" (undated); Ray Long "Central Park Skyline" (1947); and Dan MacLaughlin "Sunnyside Yards" (1964).
  - "Through Our Eyes." Otto Litzel, 1970s (Folder FF-10)
    2 items: a dust jacket for Litzel's book "Darkroom Magic" and a thumbnail reproduction of "The Artist," photograph by Bill Berriell.
  - "Through Our Eyes." PWCC Members, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    "Blue Nude" photograph series (5) by Evelyn Leif. Curriculum vita of Myron Brenton, Carolyn Bross, and Paul Knowles. Exhibition announcements and other ephemera concerning Dan Hines, Rosemary Peters and Yaqui Yamdrok.
  - "Eight Decades of Photography.", 1948-2017 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    Modern prints of photographs shown in the exhibition, identified by the wall they were mounted on; images of the backing of various photographs, showing award and other labels; Soho gallery layout used for the exhibition; publicity piece; and three "Archives Matter" newsletters from the PWCC Archives Committee leading up to the exhibition. Also holds an original 1948 certificate from the Metropolitan Camera Club Council recognizing The Hypo Hounds as a club member in good standing and a board with original award ribbons from the Council, circa 1950-60s.
  - "Eight Decades of Photography." Miscellaneous (Folder FF-11)
    Includes sheets of what appears to be wrapping paper, with exhibition images and themes. Also includes oversize reproductions of text and content related to the exhibition.
  - "Just One Day Old." Ryan Center Exhibit, 2016 March (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Print of digital reproduction of Harry Noah's photograph. Formerly in frame as presented at the Ryan Center exhibition; unframed during processing. Photocopy of exhibit label from backing is in folder.
- Series IV: Photography by Members, 1940s-2000s; 8.24 Linear feet in two boxes plus flat files
  This series contains original photographic work by club members. Most of these are individual prints, often mounted on backing material, ranging from the 1940s into at least the 1970s, though most are undated. The work of Harry Noah is especially well-represented in these photos. Many of the photographs and their backing are water damaged, as they were rescued from a flooded room.
  In addition, the series includes photographs from an album maintained by the club. These photographs are by more recent members, and date from the 1990s into the 2000s. Most of these prints are black and white, though many are in color. Finally, the series includes slides by some recent members, principally Myron Brenton. Brenton's slides are of various New York City scenes, including scenes at Ground Zero after the 9/11 attacks on the World Trade Center.
  A digitized slide show produced by the PWCC that includes some of these images and others can be seen here.
  The series is arranged by format, with single photographs followed by those from the album and then slides. Within the single photographs, the arrangement is by photographer. Box 3 holds photos that are 8x11 inches or somewhat larger; flat files (FF) hold large mounted photos; and Box 4 holds photos of a size that fall between those two. Titles of work found on the print itself are noted in "quotation marks" in the container list; titles or descriptions provided by the processing archivist are noted in [brackets].
  - Apple, Bill, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    "Band Rehearsal"
  - Arnold, M.D., undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    [Untitled, referred to by PWCC as "Little Girl with Bonnet."]
  - Arrington, Wally, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    "At the Top of the Stairs" [depicts a boy gazing into a rowhouse entrance].
  - Arrington, Wally, 1968 (Folder FF-1)
    2 photographs: "Window" [2 children at apartment window] and "Little Brother" [two boys on train or waiting area?]. PWCC stamped and dated on back of both.
  - Arthur, Dan, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    [Untitled; profile portrait of young woman in hat and with large necklace].
  - Ayles, Edith, undated (Folder FF-1)
    1 photograph: "I'm Done" [African-American young boy taking off his bib, beverage container in front of him]
  - Bernstein, Marion, 1964 (Folder FF-1)
    1 photograph: [Untitled. Alternative descriptions used by PWCC include "85 St, CPW, rain" and "Man with Umbrella."]
  - Cooke, Geraldine, circa 1964 (Folder FF-1)
    1 photograph: ["Bird in Flight"]. Exhibition stamps on back. Noted as "runner-up for Print of the Year, 1964-65."
  - Diederich, W., 1962 February (Folder FF-1)
    1 photograph: "Superman" [boy with arms spread in loose overclothes].
  - Goddard, Jr., Arthur H., undated (Folder FF-2)
    1 photograph: "The Limited" [portion of exposed building framework].
  - Goldstein, Philip, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    [Untitled; man standing against a pillar in a subway station]
  - Gooding, Roger, 1964, undated (Folder FF-2)
    3 photographs: "Rhythm" [African-American man and woman dancing or otherwise moving in harmony], 1964; "Moonlight Beach", undated; "Study in Triangular Design" [top of telephone pole and wires], undated.
  - Gurnee, Hal, undated (Folder FF-2)
    1 photograph: [Untitled. Elderly woman sitting outside large double doors of a building, appears to be outside the U.S.]
  - Harris, Linda, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    "Supper" [African-American man having a bowl of soup]
  - Jackson, Ann, undated (Folder FF-2)
    2 photographs: "Cocktails for One" [elderly man in relaxed dress enjoying a drink with garbage can lids as his side table]; "New York Summer" [children in fountain].
  - Jimenez, Ines, 1976 April 19 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    [Untitled; Profile portrait of young woman]
  - Jordan, Ed, undated (Folder FF-3)
    1 photograph: "Central Park"
  - Jordan, G. Steve, undated (Folder FF-3)
    2 photographs: "Hale House Babies" and [Untitled; referred to as Hale House Prayer by PWCC].
  - Lax, Angelina, undated (Folder FF-4)
    2 photographs: "The Road" [road with towering rock walls, traveled by truck and burro?], undated; "Tombstone" [detail of angel face], 1974.
  - Litzel, Otto, 1949, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Two photographs: "Two Leaves" (1949), noted as having received first prize in an unidentified competition, and untitled piece [fishing boats].
  - Long, Ray, 1940s? (Box 3, Folder 1)
    [Untitled; View of Manhattan skyline at night, including RCA building and Essex House, looking south from inside Central Park]
  - Lyngsted, Hanne, undated (Folder FF-4)
    1 photograph: "Meditation" [profile portrait of African-American woman]
  - MacLaughlin, Don, circa 1964 (Folder FF-4)
    1 photograph: "Long Island City" [tracks in train yard]. Exhibition stamps on back. Noted as "runner-up for Print of the Year, 1964-65."
  - Mangan, Doreen, undated (Folder FF-4)
    1 photograph: "Rooftops and Chimney Pots."
  - Muster, Regina, undated (Folder FF-4)
    1 photograph: "Bird Lady."
  - Nasoff, W., undated (Folder FF-7)
    1 photograph: "Waiting," [woman at airport].
  - Noah, Harry, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    "Self-Portrait" [while shaving]. Also referred to as "Scraping an Acquaintance."
  - Noah, Harry, 1952-1957, undated (Folder FF-5)
    10 photographs that tend to focus on people as a subject: "Shell Seekers," undated; "Just One Day Old," [boy holding pony], 15 March 1955; "Twilight Stroller," undated; [Title block obscured by one of several competition and exhibition labels on back; subject is a young man carrying artworks, circa 1952]; "August," [children and others under fire hydrant spray], circa 1957, with several labels, including First Prize from Dyckman Camera Club; "Trio," [three young boys looking at a magazine], April 1955, with several labels, including Fourth Prize at Dyckman Camera Club; "The Ash Can Kid," undated, with labels, including First Prize from Dyckman Camera Club; "Hope Springs Eternal," [man on stoop reading Racing Form], circa 1957; "Autumn Chore," [man raking and burning leaves], undated; "Derelict," [man in doorway at night clutching bag], undated.
  - Noah, Harry, 1954-1965, undated (Folder FF-6)
    8 photographs that tend to focus on buildings and things other than people: "Foggy Run" [train at station], undated; "The Old Time Religion" [rural church building], 1961; "Old MacDonald Had a Farm," 1963; "Rough Trail" [walking in park through deep snow], undated; "Buds and Buddies" [flowers and birds], undated; "The Square Knot," 1965; "Japanesque," [shoreline evoking the style of a Japanese garden], undated; "The Clouds Go Rolling By," 1954, labeled as having won Second Prize at the Dyckman Camera Club. Several have competition/exhibition stamps on back.
  - Padernacht, Sandra (Sandy), undated (Folder FF-7)
    4 photographs: "Woman with Book"; "Back"; "Man with Bass"; "Young Black Woman."
  - Rivera, Primitivo, undated (Folder FF-7)
    1 photograph: "Covered with Sand" [boy buried in sand except for his head]
  - Rogers, Linda, undated (Folder FF-7)
    1 photograph: "Caftan Contrasts"
  - Ruth, Sura, undated (Folder FF-7)
    2 portrait photographs of a woman, one titled "Profile" and the other referred to as "Chin" by PWCC because of the camera angle, though the actual name on back is now obscured.
  - Schnaebele, Ernest, undated (Folder FF-8)
    1 photograph: "Triangles" [weathered, migrant(?) housing in field].
  - Schneider, Herb, undated (Folder FF-8)
    1 photograph (color): "World Trade Center and Church"
  - Shulman, R., 1974 (Folder FF-8)
    1 photograph: "Eileen" [portrait of a young woman]
  - Stuart, Ron, 1978 May 14 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    "Double Exposure at an Antique Store"
  - Taplin, Claire, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    3 photographs: "Against the Wall" [four elderly people on a bench]; "Village Fountain" [elderly woman getting water]; and "Grandmother & Nina."
  - Unidentified Photographers, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Two photographs, both untitled. One depicts a couple on a wooded hillside looking out over a river; the photo is torn with part missing. The second photo is of a mannequin.
  - Unidentified Photographers, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    2 photographs: One is an untitled photo, with 3 prints, of a woman in curlers getting her done done by a hairdresser, who is also in curlers. A banner on the salon wall reads "Hairdressers give the best blow jobs." A second is also untitled and is of four boys playing at the fence of a wood house.
  - Unidentified Photographer, undated (Folder FF-8)
    1 photograph (color-tinted): [Clouds]
  - Watson, Gordon, circa 1980? (Folder FF-8)
    1 photograph: "Ancient Wood"
  - Weiner, Mabel, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    [Untitled; African-American child hiding and peeking out from behind the leg of a woman, both subjects in tattered clothing]
  - Weiss, Martin, undated (Folder FF-8)
    1 photograph: "Old Man" [profile portrait]
  - Photograph Album (folder 1 of 2), 1996-1997, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Photographs, most untitled, by Godfrey Fred Aquilino (1) "The Jug Sellers of Delhi"; Carolyn Bross (10 from 1996-97, in color), "Schoolroom," "I Pledge Allegiance," "The Old Stove," "Window in a Windmill," "Wisteria," "Yellow Bench,"Time Honored Tradition," "Girl with Red Lipstick," "Broken Mirror and Daffodils"; Marilyn Fish-Glynn (4) "Ellis Island" and 3 untitled; Rosemary Peters (1), "Boston/Willows"; Anthony Venezio (4, in color); Yaqui Yamdrok (5); and unidentified (6, two in color).
  - Photograph Album (folder 2 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Photographs, most untitled, by: Florence Forman (1), "Chinese Man in Doorway"; Ruth Formanek (4); Anthony Venezio (2, in color); and unidentified (6, four in color).
  - Slides. Brenton, Myron, circa 1990s-2001 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Approximately 400 color slides. The subject most represented is Ground Zero in the aftermath of the 9/11 attacks on the World Trade Center. Other subjects include graffiti/wall art, construction sites, Coney Island, West Indian Day Parade, street fairs and festivals, the Brooklyn Bridge, and Central Park. Several sheets of slides are labeled "NYC Misc"; these appear to often fit into the above categories and are often of people and street scenes. and people
  - Slides. Wallace, Marie, circa 2000s (Box 3, Folder 4)
    7 color slides of nature scenes and buildings.
  - Slides. Various Photographers, circa 2000s (Box 3, Folder 5)
    32 slides (color and black and white) by various photographers. Identified photographers are Myron Brenton, Marilyn Fish-Glynn, Ruth Formanek, Myrna Harrison-Changar, Paul Knowles, Rosemary Peters, Helen B. Pine, Susan Sigrist, and Yaqui Yamdrok.